<Document>
# Standard Operating Procedure (SOP)

Standard Operating Procedure is a set of Guidelines to be followed when the station is functioning nominally. Breaching Standard Operating Procedure without a very good reason is grounds for demotion, at the discretion of the relevant Head of Staff. In addition, blindly following the letter of SOP while ignoring the context of the shift is a [bold]bad idea[/bold]. SOP is malleable if the situation requires it, and the general well-being and proper functioning of the crew and station should not be sacrificed for the sake of rigorous adherence of SOP. Remember, [bold]context is king[/bold].

## Alert Levels

### Code Green

[bold]Conditions:[/bold]

- Default Alert Code at the start of the shift. Do not change unless a threat is suspected/confirmed.

[bold]OR[/bold]

- All confirmed/suspected threats to the station and/or crew have been handled, or simply vanished on their own. It is recommended that, after 15+ minutes on Code Blue without any hostile activity, Code Green be called.

[bold]Security:[/bold]

- All weapons must be holstered or kept in pockets/suit storage slots unless absolutely required.
- Long arms must remain inside of the brig, exceptions made for the HoS who may carry their energy shotgun.

- Random searches are not permitted without express permission by either the Head of Security, or Captain. However, searches are still permitted if there is reasonable suspicion of a crime.

[bold]Secure Areas:[/bold] EVA Storage, Tech Storage, Gravity Generator, Engineering Secure Storage, Vault, anywhere else requiring command level access that does not get regularly used

- Secure areas are to be left unbolted and ready to be used for their intended purposes.

- The Vault is not to be opened unless repairs are required, gold is required for Science, or a critical item needs to be hidden in the safe.

### Code Blue

[bold]Conditions:[/bold]

- There is a suspected threat on-board the station, or at a nearby location in space. This includes any signs of hostile activity that have not caused any damage to station or crew, but nonetheless seem present.

[bold]OR[/bold]

- Confirmed Code Red threats have been properly handled or subsided on their own. It is recommended that, after 15+ minutes on Code Red without any hostile activity, Code Blue be called.

[bold]Security:[/bold]

- Weapons do not need to be holstered.

- Long arms permitted outside of the brig.

- Random searches are fully permitted. Security personnel may detain any personnel refusing a random search.

[bold]Secure Areas:[/bold] EVA Storage, Tech Storage, Gravity Generator, Engineering Secure Storage, Vault, anywhere else requiring command level access that does not get regularly used

- It is recommended that all Secure Areas be bolted down unless their use is necessary.

[bold]General Crew:[/bold]

- Personnel are to report any suspicious activity to the nearest member of Security, or use common radio if urgent.

- Personnel are highly encouraged to exercise caution, even if the threat is only suspected. Following simple safety procedures (such as not going through Maintenance alone).

- Visitors to the station such as refugees are recommended to stay in public areas, for their safety.

### Code Violet

[bold]Conditions:[/bold]

- There is a confirmed viral outbreak on the station.

[bold]Security[/bold]

- Use of long rifles and other gear is permitted.

- Security officers should work to contain the threat and protect the crew.

[bold]Medical[/bold]

- Medical personal should immidetly begin work on a cure or vaccine for the infection.

- Attempts to treat infected patients that have begin showing symptoms is discouraged.

### Code Red

[bold]Conditions:[/bold]

- There is a confirmed, hostile threat on-board the station or nearby in space. This threat should pose recognizable danger to the station and/or crew at large.

[bold]Security:[/bold]

- Random searches are fully permitted and recommended. Security personnel may detain any personnel refusing a random search in order to conduct said search.

- Security personnel are to cooperate fully with any Central Command Staff (such as Emergency Response Teams) in order to eliminate the threat to the station.

[bold]Secure Areas:[/bold] EVA Storage, Tech Storage, Gravity Generator, Engineering Secure Storage, Vault, anywhere else requiring command level access that does not get regularly used

- There are no restrictions on bolting Secure Areas. Secure Areas may be left bolted or unbolted at the discretion of Command personnel.

[bold]General Crew:[/bold]

- Personnel are to follow the instructions of Security staff, so long as they are within the bounds of Space Law and are not acting against the general well-being of the station and its crew.

## Line of succession

If the captain dies and is unrecoverable for whatever reason, then a new captain must be selected. This follows a fairly simple ruling which has a step by step guide:

- Step 1: Is captain still alive? if so proceed to step 5, if not proceed to the next step.
- Step 2: Is hop still alive? if so proceed to step 5, if not proceed to the next step.
- Step 3: All heads may vote on a head to make captain, then should proceed to step 5, If all heads are dead proceed to the next step.
- Step 4: Call the shuttle and set the alert level to code red.
- Step 5: That person is now Captain.

## High Risk Equipment

Each command member features a piece of equipment that is highly sought after by members of the syndicate. They should either remain in the respective head's possession or in their round-start locker. These items should not be given out unless in extreme situations and not permanently. Exceptions are made for handing off equipment to mindshielded crew members (HoS handing the shotgun to the Warden). The list of items is as follows:

- Captain's ID
- Captain's Jetpack
- Captain's Antique Laser
- Nuclear Authentication Disk
- CMO's Hypospray
- CMO's Handheld Crew Monitor
- RD's Experimental Research Hardsuit
- RD's Hand Teleporter
- QM's Digiboard
- CE's Advanced Magboots
- HoS' Energy Shotgun

## Docking and Visitors

### Visitors

- The station is encouraged to allow non-hostile visitors permission to dock or otherwise come aboard during normal operating conditions.
- If an individual commits a crime aboard a Nanotrasen station, and then flees to an actively in-use unaffiliated vessel, habitat, or station, it is up to that organisation to offer or reject a request for asylum.
- The Captain may grant or deny asylum at his discretion.
- Visitors may be granted whatever access the Captain deems appropriate.
- Visitors may be assigned an escort or searched upon entrance at the Captain’s discretion, however at no times should the crew enter a visitor’s vessel without permission, search a visitor’s vessel, or otherwise infringe on their sovereignty.
- Visitors aboard an NT Vessel are subject to Space Law. Likewise, if a visitor breaks the law and then immediately flees to their own vessel, the "hot pursuit" doctrine applies and security may board to detain.

### Vessels

- Any personnel aboard a vessel are under the legal authority of that vessel and may be legally fined, arrested, detained, and otherwise punished for infractions of the visitor's laws.
- Vessels belonging to organizations at war with Nanotrasen, or vessels which attack a Nanotrasen facility or ship are not protected by these regulations, nor are vessels engaged in blatant criminal activities such as human slavery.

## Hiring/Transfering

- No new hires or transfers are permitted without contacting the relevant Head of Staff. If one is not available, promoting an Acting Head of Staff is recommended. If none is available, the Head of Personnel/Captain are to utilize their best judgement.
- Promotion to Acting Head of Staff requires authorization by the Captain or Acting Captain.
- All new hires to the Security Department, or acting heads of staff, are to be mindshield and searched for contraband.

## Demotion Procedure

- No demotions are to be performed without authorization from the relevant Head of Staff or Captain.
- Personnel are to report to the Head of Personnel for demotion.
- After a demotion order is given to the person being demoted (e.g: by radio), that person is no longer considered a member of that department. Security may take further legal actions if the person does not fully comply.

### Causes for Demotion

(This list is not exhaustive, these are key examples)

- Any major crime or higher.
- Critical incompetence at a given job.
- Refusal to follow legal and relevant orders by the respective Head of Staff. Legality and relevance of said orders are to be judged by the Captain or Head of Personnel.
- Creation of an abusive or unsafe work environment.
- Abandoning a given job for more than 15 minutes at a time.

## Lawful Orders

- Department heads may give direct, lawful orders to any station personnel reporting to them or to another of their subordinates.
- When receiving conflicting lawful orders coming from two distinct persons of authority, whether by role (department head) or by law (security), station personnel cannot be held liable and charged with failure to comply with one of the redundant orders.
- Command staff is held liable for their staff when giving a direct order and may be charged criminally if their missives are not lawful

## Nuclear Operative Presence

- All weapons and chemical restrictions are lifted.
- Cargo should focus on requesting as many weapons as possible. Security is to be prioritized for distribution, but regular personnel may also be armed.
- Science should work in tandem with salvage/cargo in order to fabricate weapons and equipment for combat.
- Building defenses and fortifying key locations is recommended.
- The emergency shuttle is only to be called once the operatives have been eliminated, or have stalled their attack.

## Departments

### Captain

- The Captain’s primary purpose is to delegate work among their command staff, and ensure all departments are running efficiently.
- The Captain is not permitted to perform regular Security Duty. However, they may still assist Security if they are understaffed, or if they see a crime being committed. However, the Captain is not permitted to take items from the Armory under normal circumstances, unless authorized by the Head of Security. In addition, the Captain may not requisition weaponry beyond their own, unless there's an immediate threat to station and/or crew.
- If a Department lacks a Head of Staff, the Captain should make reasonable efforts to appoint an Acting Head of Staff, if there are available personnel to fill the position;
- The Captain is not to leave the Station,
- The Captain must ensure the nuke disk is in their possession at all times.
- The Captain may only promote personnel to a Acting Head of Staff position if there is no assigned Head of Staff associated with the Department. Said Acting Head of Staff must be a member of the Department they are to lead.
- The Captain may not fire any Head of Staff without reasonable justification. Firing personnel should be left to the respective head of staff, or head of personnel.

### Head of Personnel

- The Head of Personnel may not transfer any personnel to another Department without authorization from the relevant Head of Staff. (See Hiring/Transferring for more)
- The Head of Personnel may not give any personnel increased access without authorization from the relevant Head of Staff. This includes the Head of Personnel. In addition, the Head of Personnel may only give Captain-Level access to someone if they are the Acting Captain. This access is to be removed when a proper Captain arrives on the station.
- The Head of Personnel may not fire any personnel without authorization from the relevant Head of Staff. (See demotion procedure for more)
- The Head of Personnel is free to utilize paperwork at their discretion. However, during major station emergencies, expediency should take precedence over bureaucracy.
- The Head of Personnel may not leave their office unmanned if there are personnel waiting in line. If not at their office, they should actively be on the lookout for radio calls requesting them at their office.
- The Head of Personnel is not permitted to perform Security duty.

### Quartermaster

- The Quartermaster must ensure that every approved order is delivered within a reasonable time frame.
- The Quartermaster is not permitted to authorize the ordering of Security equipment and/or gear without express permission from the Head of Security and/or Captain. An exception is made during extreme emergencies, such as Nuclear Operatives or a wizard incursion.
- The Quartermaster is permitted to authorize non-departmental orders (such as a Medical Doctor asking for Insulated Gloves) without express permission from the respective Head of Staff (in this example, the Chief Engineer), utilizing their best judgement, although they may still request a stamped form or verbal permission.
- The Quartermaster is not permitted to authorize a singularity or tesla generator without permission from the Chief Engineer.

### Chief Engineer

- The Chief Engineer must make sure that the station’s electrical engines are fully set up and supplying power to the station.
- The Chief Engineer is responsible for maintaining the integrity of Telecommunications.
- The Chief Engineer is responsible for maintaining the integrity of all engines set up on the station, and ensuring the department is performing routine maintenance on their respective engines.
- The Chief Engineer is responsible for assisting with maintaining the station’s atmospheric systems.

### Research Director

- The Research Director must make sure Research is being done. There should be an attempt to research as many technologies before the shift ends.
- The Research Director is permitted to change the Stations AI’s laws, provided they receive general approval from other members of command.
- The Research Director is to ensure the safety of the crew by maintaining active anomalies, and preventing alien artifacts from leaving the science department. Artifacts should be placed in containment units before being transported.
- Ensure that anomalies near departments have given their consent for the anomaly to remain active.
- Work in tandem with the Chief Medical Officer to ensure unrecoverable patients have consented to being borged.

### Chief Medical Officer

- The Chief Medical Officer must ensure that all crew members receive adequate medical care.
- The Chief Medical Officer must ensure that corpses are properly stored, and those who can’t be revived should be detailed as to why that is not possible.
- The Chief Medical Officer must ensure that there are adequate medical reagents to treat all types of damage.
- Work in tandem with the Research Director to ensure unrecoverable patients have consented to being borged.

</Document>
